<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Debian on </title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/tags/debian/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Debian on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/debian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The year of Linux Desktop</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/linux_desktop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/linux_desktop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-did-i-end-up-here&#34;&gt;How did I end up here?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year was 2016 when I met Richard Stallman, father of the Free Software movement
and GNU operating system. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard about Linux before but Richard definitely open
my world to new possibilities. I tried a couple of Linux distributions Fedora and
Mint, overall I liked more Fedora but it was way easier to use Mint in a daily basis.
However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t stick to it, I changed my Macbook at the time to a Windows laptop and just moved on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-did-i-end-up-here&#34;&gt;How did I end up here?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year was 2016 when I met Richard Stallman, father of the Free Software movement
and GNU operating system. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard about Linux before but Richard definitely open
my world to new possibilities. I tried a couple of Linux distributions Fedora and
Mint, overall I liked more Fedora but it was way easier to use Mint in a daily basis.
However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t stick to it, I changed my Macbook at the time to a Windows laptop and just moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2021 I went back to Mac and that was when I started to see the shortcomings of operating systems.
For development I love Unix based systems is easy to navigate and use but to be honest
I think I rather use Windows on a daily basis. That being said, I think Windows and MacOS
suck in their own way. Windows feels like spyware more and more and MacOS is so opinionated in their UI
that it can be very frustrating, plus the new AI stuff in both is not great for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-serious-about-linux&#34;&gt;Getting serious about Linux&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I can be a little bit of a rebel, and conform with the norm is not
really my thing. My best friend sent me an article about a guy who tried daily drive Linux and never went back.
It really scratch that part of my brain that make me obsess over things.
I stared slow, I wanted Excel but I have a Mac, and I freaking hate Numbers, but needed something to work,
specially since we work with China and they can&amp;rsquo;t use Google. The solution was LibreOffice.
Turns out you can personalise you your software, what? Is this free as in freedom?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my current job I was tasked to create a new and shiny tech infrastructure.
Moving from text messages and google suite to an actual system for our processes of
sourcing, project management and sales. The two winners: Slack and Odoo (Open source ERP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Odoo have a community edition that you can run on premise. I needed to test the product
so I decided to run a virtual machine with Debian. Why Debian?, I wanted something lean,
Odoo recommended Ubuntu and I thought, well, Debian is like the father of Ubuntu, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debian 12 was extremely easy to install, I went into the rabbit hole, what is a Desktop Environment?,
tiling window manager?, Arch with Hyprland? I tried them all, even XFCE with i3 instead of it&amp;rsquo;s native window manager.
I can honestly say I have installed Debian 20 times by now, running the Odoo service was way
more complicated than expected, connecting the PSQL to DBeaver, another day, haha.
Everything took ages, but honestly, it was amazing, I could do whatever I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to buy a second hand Thinkpad as my personal computer and use Debian as my main
OS. Turns out KDE is great and now I daily drive Sway. I found The Primeagen, Josean, Typecraft, Linux Cast,
Distrotube, DHH, Diinki. An amazing community where we all think that our computer should be ours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increasing amount of time I spent in the terminal made me dive into CLI tools like TMUX, Neovim and Yazi.
I became keyboard centric, now I use Home Rows and an ergonomic keyboard.
Honestly, I think Linux made me a better professional. I not only use software now,
I am passionate about it, I am not afraid of not knowing or an endless documentation.
The about of frustration you get from failing to change something in you config is
rewarded with resilience and accomplishment. I love computers now, they are not only
tools I use, they say something about me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
