<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The year of Linux Desktop</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/linux_desktop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/linux_desktop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-did-i-end-up-here&#34;&gt;How did I end up here?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year was 2016 when I met Richard Stallman, father of the Free Software movement
and GNU operating system. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard about Linux before but Richard definitely open
my world to new possibilities. I tried a couple of Linux distributions Fedora and
Mint, overall I liked more Fedora but it was way easier to use Mint in a daily basis.
However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t stick to it, I changed my Macbook at the time to a Windows laptop and just moved on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-did-i-end-up-here&#34;&gt;How did I end up here?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year was 2016 when I met Richard Stallman, father of the Free Software movement
and GNU operating system. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard about Linux before but Richard definitely open
my world to new possibilities. I tried a couple of Linux distributions Fedora and
Mint, overall I liked more Fedora but it was way easier to use Mint in a daily basis.
However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t stick to it, I changed my Macbook at the time to a Windows laptop and just moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2021 I went back to Mac and that was when I started to see the shortcomings of operating systems.
For development I love Unix based systems is easy to navigate and use but to be honest
I think I rather use Windows on a daily basis. That being said, I think Windows and MacOS
suck in their own way. Windows feels like spyware more and more and MacOS is so opinionated in their UI
that it can be very frustrating, plus the new AI stuff in both is not great for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-serious-about-linux&#34;&gt;Getting serious about Linux&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I can be a little bit of a rebel, and conform with the norm is not
really my thing. My best friend sent me an article about a guy who tried daily drive Linux and never went back.
It really scratch that part of my brain that make me obsess over things.
I stared slow, I wanted Excel but I have a Mac, and I freaking hate Numbers, but needed something to work,
specially since we work with China and they can&amp;rsquo;t use Google. The solution was LibreOffice.
Turns out you can personalise you your software, what? Is this free as in freedom?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my current job I was tasked to create a new and shiny tech infrastructure.
Moving from text messages and google suite to an actual system for our processes of
sourcing, project management and sales. The two winners: Slack and Odoo (Open source ERP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Odoo have a community edition that you can run on premise. I needed to test the product
so I decided to run a virtual machine with Debian. Why Debian?, I wanted something lean,
Odoo recommended Ubuntu and I thought, well, Debian is like the father of Ubuntu, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debian 12 was extremely easy to install, I went into the rabbit hole, what is a Desktop Environment?,
tiling window manager?, Arch with Hyprland? I tried them all, even XFCE with i3 instead of it&amp;rsquo;s native window manager.
I can honestly say I have installed Debian 20 times by now, running the Odoo service was way
more complicated than expected, connecting the PSQL to DBeaver, another day, haha.
Everything took ages, but honestly, it was amazing, I could do whatever I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to buy a second hand Thinkpad as my personal computer and use Debian as my main
OS. Turns out KDE is great and now I daily drive Sway. I found The Primeagen, Josean, Typecraft, Linux Cast,
Distrotube, DHH, Diinki. An amazing community where we all think that our computer should be ours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increasing amount of time I spent in the terminal made me dive into CLI tools like TMUX, Neovim and Yazi.
I became keyboard centric, now I use Home Rows and an ergonomic keyboard.
Honestly, I think Linux made me a better professional. I not only use software now,
I am passionate about it, I am not afraid of not knowing or an endless documentation.
The about of frustration you get from failing to change something in you config is
rewarded with resilience and accomplishment. I love computers now, they are not only
tools I use, they say something about me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Revamp</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello there, it&amp;rsquo;s been a while since I wanted to do some changes to my website, but the thought of learning a JavaScript framework made me drag my feet a lot. As you know, I am not a web developer, but I love software and learning new things. Fortunately, I found Hugo, an open source framework for static websites and blogs written in Go. The best thing about it is that I can write my entries in Markdown and Hugo will make the HTML. One of the things that I really wanted to explore is blogging, and Hugo is fantastic for that. I can do it directly in my terminal and push it to my repository on GitHub. To make things easier, I am using GitHub Pages so I don&amp;rsquo;t need to worry about anything else other than the content.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Hello there, it&amp;rsquo;s been a while since I wanted to do some changes to my website, but the thought of learning a JavaScript framework made me drag my feet a lot. As you know, I am not a web developer, but I love software and learning new things. Fortunately, I found Hugo, an open source framework for static websites and blogs written in Go. The best thing about it is that I can write my entries in Markdown and Hugo will make the HTML. One of the things that I really wanted to explore is blogging, and Hugo is fantastic for that. I can do it directly in my terminal and push it to my repository on GitHub. To make things easier, I am using GitHub Pages so I don&amp;rsquo;t need to worry about anything else other than the content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, welcome to my new website and my first blog! I will write from time to time, hopefully regularly, about new projects or technologies. Since the blog is a passion project, I&amp;rsquo;d rather ship fast than make them perfect. Some of them may be half-cooked ideas, but the motivation is to share my interests and attract other people to share knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the last thing is that I want to keep the blogs short, more like microblogging. Thanks for reading, and feel free to connect with me, you&amp;rsquo;ll find my socials in the Contact menu. Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experience</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;//localhost:1313/cv-fidel.pdf&#34;&gt;Download CV (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;project-and-data-analytics-manager--lux-design--manufacturing&#34;&gt;Project and Data Analytics Manager | Lux Design + Manufacturing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 2023 – Present&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Vancouver, Canada&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployed local LLMs with Ollama and Open WebUI in a docker container&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed Python scripts utilising Monday.com GraphQL API to extract project data, transforming nested JSON responses into flattened CSV format for seamless Looker Studio integration and cross-departmental reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defined, implemented, tested and deployed ERP system increasing response time by 200% in purchase and sales orders traceability and productivity at the overseas warehouse in Asia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage 100% of data infrastructure and expanded tech stack from 3 to 9 integrated systems over 18 months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborated with 5 different departments to ensure alignment, resulting in 30% reduction in cross-departmental miscommunications and enhanced customer experience delivery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led cross-functional projects, ensuring timely delivery within budget and scope while maintaining focus on customer-centric outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan and execute software development of internal web apps as well as client portal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data modelling and architecture design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define tech stack for digitalisation of the company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;support-engineer--amazon-audible&#34;&gt;Support Engineer | Amazon (Audible)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 2023 – August 2023&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Mexico City, Mexico&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;//localhost:1313/cv-fidel.pdf&#34;&gt;Download CV (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;project-and-data-analytics-manager--lux-design--manufacturing&#34;&gt;Project and Data Analytics Manager | Lux Design + Manufacturing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 2023 – Present&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Vancouver, Canada&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployed local LLMs with Ollama and Open WebUI in a docker container&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed Python scripts utilising Monday.com GraphQL API to extract project data, transforming nested JSON responses into flattened CSV format for seamless Looker Studio integration and cross-departmental reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defined, implemented, tested and deployed ERP system increasing response time by 200% in purchase and sales orders traceability and productivity at the overseas warehouse in Asia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage 100% of data infrastructure and expanded tech stack from 3 to 9 integrated systems over 18 months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborated with 5 different departments to ensure alignment, resulting in 30% reduction in cross-departmental miscommunications and enhanced customer experience delivery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led cross-functional projects, ensuring timely delivery within budget and scope while maintaining focus on customer-centric outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan and execute software development of internal web apps as well as client portal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data modelling and architecture design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define tech stack for digitalisation of the company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;support-engineer--amazon-audible&#34;&gt;Support Engineer | Amazon (Audible)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 2023 – August 2023&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Mexico City, Mexico&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implemented patches for Java-based content pipelines in AWS, ensuring system security and reliability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed AWS Cloud Practitioner and Solutions Architect course, gaining proficiency in cloud computing fundamentals, infrastructure and AWS services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-analyst--undostres&#34;&gt;Data Analyst | Undostres&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 2022 – June 2023&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Mexico City, Mexico&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed automated reporting processes with Jenkins, Python, and MySQL, cutting processing time by 50% and enabling faster insights for customer program evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employed advanced SQL optimisation techniques including indexes, temporary tables, and window functions for enhanced data retrieval and customer behaviour analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Utilised data analytics techniques to analyse customer LTV, engagement patterns, and transactional funnels, providing actionable insights for customer acquisition and retention strategies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created financial dashboards highlighting seasonalities and outliers, supporting strategic decision-making for customer programs and business growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;business-intelligence-analyst--valoreo&#34;&gt;Business Intelligence Analyst | Valoreo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;October 2021 – April 2022&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Mexico City, Mexico&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created supply chain reports with Looker Studio and BigQuery, filling critical gaps and providing actionable insights for cross-functional decision makers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborated with business stakeholders and data engineering teams to develop stable data pipelines supporting customer program measurement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planned and prioritised projects using agile methodologies in Jira, focussing on fast delivery through sprint-based development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;analytics-consultant--energea&#34;&gt;Analytics Consultant | EnergeA&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 2021 – October 2021&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Mexico City, Mexico&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducted economic appraisals and financial analyses within the Oil &amp;amp; Gas and renewable energy sectors, focussing on financial viability and strategic investments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provided data-driven strategic insights and recommendations through comprehensive economic assessments, supporting clients in operational efficiency optimisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills&#34;&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SQL, Python, Bash, Git, BigQuery, Looker Studio, MS Excel, Tableau, Monday.com, Project Management, Linux, Data Visualisation, Data Modelling, Dashboard Creation, SQL Optimisation, ETL, Data cleansing, Stakeholder Management, Agile methodologies, GCP, AWS, Jenkins (CI/CD), Prompt Engineering, ChatGPT, Claude, Claude Code, Gemini, Local LLMs, Machine Learning, Odoo, Odoo.sh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;business-administration--ebc&#34;&gt;Business Administration | EBC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019 – 2021&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s Degree&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highest GPA in graduating class (9.83/10.00)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fastest program completion in school history (completed in 3 years instead of 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;helicopter-and-airplane-pilot&#34;&gt;Helicopter and Airplane Pilot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2017 – 2018&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Private Pilot Licence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;applied-mathematics--itam&#34;&gt;Applied Mathematics | ITAM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2012 – 2017&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;em&gt;Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s Degree&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to My Digital Workshop</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a data analyst passionate about building robust solutions with open-source technologies and software development. My work centres around transforming complex data into actionable insights and developing efficient, scalable applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-do&#34;&gt;What I Do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I specialise in data analytics and software development, with a particular focus on Python-based solutions and SQL-driven data processing. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s building automated data pipelines, creating analytical dashboards, or developing custom applications, I believe in leveraging the right tools for each challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a data analyst passionate about building robust solutions with open-source technologies and software development. My work centres around transforming complex data into actionable insights and developing efficient, scalable applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-do&#34;&gt;What I Do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I specialise in data analytics and software development, with a particular focus on Python-based solutions and SQL-driven data processing. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s building automated data pipelines, creating analytical dashboards, or developing custom applications, I believe in leveraging the right tools for each challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My technical toolkit includes Python for data analysis and application development, SQL for database design and complex queries, and bash/zsh scripting for automation. I&amp;rsquo;m also proficient with Excel for rapid prototyping and stakeholder communication, and I use neovim and tmux for efficient development workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-philosophy&#34;&gt;My Philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a strong advocate for open-source software and the Unix philosophy of doing one thing well. My preferred development environment runs on Debian Linux, where I appreciate the stability, security, and flexibility that comes with a well-maintained distribution. This foundation allows me to focus on what matters most: solving problems and delivering value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-youll-find-here&#34;&gt;What You&amp;rsquo;ll Find Here&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog serves as both a technical journal and a resource for fellow developers and analysts. I share insights from my projects, explore new technologies, and document solutions to challenges I encounter. You&amp;rsquo;ll find posts ranging from data analysis techniques and Python best practices to Linux system administration and development workflow optimisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;rsquo;re here to learn about a specific technical topic or to explore potential collaboration opportunities, I&amp;rsquo;m glad you stopped by. Feel free to reach out if you&amp;rsquo;d like to discuss a project or simply connect with a fellow technology enthusiast.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
